Emergency Committee on the Transportation Crisis 036
People's Archive, MLK Library
Emergency Committee on the Transportation Crisis Records
1960-1978
People's Archive, MLK Library
Emergency Committee on the Transportation Crisis
036
72 Boxes
23.5 Linear feet
Arrangement
Series 1: Alphabetical Files, 8 linear ft. (1960-1978). This series contains alphabetically arranged topical files that document ECTC's activities as well as those of other related organizations. The records were primarily maintained by Anne and Fred Huette - Corresponding Secretary, and Vice Chair of ECTC; and Angela and Thomas Rooney - Executive Secretary, and Associate Executive Secretary of ECTC. In order to maintain the original order, this series has been arranged into subseries by the persons who maintained the records.
Subseries 1: Rooney Files, 2.5 linear ft. (1965-1975). This sub-series contains address lists, correspondence, publications, flyers, notes, and correspondence related to civic organizations in northeast D.C. such as the Brookland Civic Association, Brookland Area Coordinating Council, and the Catholic Interracial Council. Reports from various governmental agencies, including the D.C. Office of Planning and Management, the National Capital Planning Commission, and the D.C. Department of Transportation appear in the files. Other file topics include parking in D.C., pollution, D.C. buses, home rule, housing, and zoning. Interfiled among the records are also a number of news clippings on the topics.
Subseries 2: Huette Files, 5.5 linear ft. (1968-1978). This sub-series includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, meeting minutes, clippings, and press releases related to the activities of ECTC and similar local organizations throughout the country. Of particular significance are records of the National Committee on the Transportation Crisis, the national organization that grew out of local freeway fights. Files cover the work of organizations in cities such as Boston, Philadelphia, Pittsburgh, Nashville, and Phoenix. Other topics and organizations found in the series include the Citizens Planning Coalition of D.C., the Brookland Area Coordinating Council, the Washington Planning Council, the Washington Lay Association, and the Upper Northeast Coordinating Council.
Series 2: Correspondence, 1 linear ft. (1964-1980). Much of the correspondence in this series is between members of ECTC and local politicians about highway legislation. Correspondents include public officials such as Walter Washington, Senator Joe Tydings, President Lyndon Johnson, Senator Paul Sarbanes, and Walter Tobriner, President of the Board of D.C. Commissioners (1964). The series also contains some reports, clippings, and legislative materials related to the correspondence. The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Series 3: Chronological, 1.25 linear ft. (1965-1974). This series consists of a group of items that had no apparent arrangement nor fit in other series before processing. The materials were arranged chronologically to form this series. The series includes correspondence, reports, clippings, legislative testimony and bills, handwritten notes, newsletters, articles, and flyers.
Series 4: Legislative Materials, 4 linear ft. (1965-1975). This series consists of testimony, statements, witness lists, and other background materials regarding hearings on highway construction before the D.C. City Council, D.C. Department of Highways and Traffic (DCDH), and U.S. Congressional Committees. Of particular significance are materials regarding hearings before the City Council on the Interstate Highway System (1967-1968), the DCDH (1965) on the North Central Freeway, and the House Committee on D.C. in the late 1960s on such issues as federal payment for highway funding and rapid rail transit. Copies of federal highway legislation in the Federal Register and Congressional Record are also included. Folders are arranged alphabetically by title.
Series 5: Printed Matter, 2 linear ft. (1967-1981) Printed matter including pamphlets, journal articles, government publications, newsletters, and legislative materials on topics of interest to ECTC is contained in this series. Materials are arranged alphabetically first by journal title (if applicable), otherwise by author (if known), or title of article.
Series 6: Clippings and Press Materials, 1 linear ft. (1968-1979). This series contains clippings, press releases, and related legislative items which focus primarily on freeway construction and transportation issues throughout the U.S. Clippings are not arranged. Press releases and related materials are arranged chronologically after the clippings.
Series 7: Flyers, .50 linear ft. (1969-1973; 1987-89). This series contains flyers about rallies, demonstrations, meetings, and lobbying activities sponsored by ECTC and other organizations involved in the Washington metro area freeway fight. Of significance are flyers about the fight to save the Three Sisters Bridge, rallies to protest government-confiscated homes on 10th and Franklin Streets, N.E., and public events expressing opposition to the North-Central Freeway. Other flyers cover issues about which ECTC was interested, including the environment, statehood, home rule, poverty, and racial discrimination.
Series 8: Membership, .75 linear ft. (1967; n.d.) Included in this series is a guest book of signatures from an unidentified ECTC event, blank membership cards for the Brookland Neighborhood Association (1967), and 3x5 cards with handwritten information on activist organizations of interest to ECTC.
Series 9: Photographs and Memorabilia, .50 linear ft. (1968-1979). The series contains photographs, a ECTC's bumper sticker "Save Don't Pave," a statehood flag, and other memorabilia.
Series 10: Architectural Drawings and Maps, 13.50 linear ft. (1967-1974). This series contains 64 maps, scaled drawings, sketches, and site plans of the Washington area. In particular, a number of draft and final site plans and sketches of the Brookland, Takoma, Ft. Totten, and Rhode Island Avenue Metro stations are in this series. Other items of interest include a D.C. Department of Highways major highways project map, preliminary master plans, and various maps of the North Central Freeway. The drawings and maps are numbered sequentially. An index attached to this finding aid lists the sequentially numbered items in alphabetical order for reference.
Series 11: Picket Signs and Posters, 10 linear ft. (n.d.). This series contains primarily picket signs created by ECTC members and others to protest freeway construction in the Washington metro area. Sam Abbott was the creator of many of the cartoons and caricatures on the signs. Also included are a few posters and what appear to be handwritten flip chart sheets from workshops and meetings.
Series 12: Charts and Graphs, 4 containers and 1 oversized folder (ca. 1960s). This series contains tables, charts, and graphs drawn on oversized tablets what appear to be from flip charts used for workshops or educational sessions on freeway issues in D.C.
Biographical / Historical
From the 1950s through the 1970s various plans were drafted by local and federal agencies to build a comprehensive urban expressway to link D.C. to the national interstate highway system. In the 1960s The Emergency Committee on the Transportation Crisis (ECTC) grew out of the efforts of residents in northeast D.C. and Maryland who organized to prevent government confiscation of homes in the path of the freeway.
ECTC lobbied public officials; and testified at hearings to prevent the building of the North Central Freeway through D.C and before Congress to curtail funding for highway construction. ECTC spurred the formation of the National Coalition on the Transportation Crisis, which coordinated similar grassroots movements throughout the nation. As a grassroots organization, ECTC relied on public demonstrations, rallies, and meetings to gain support for its cause in the late 1960s. In particular, ECTC was involved in a prolonged demonstration and sit-in at the construction site of the Three Sisters Bridge, held rallies to protest confiscation of homes in the Brookland neighborhood of D.C., and picketed Mayor Walter Washington's home in opposition of freeway construction. ECTC was interested in a number of related issues such as urban planning, environmental issues, home rule, D.C. statehood, and civil rights. It also supported a metrorail system as an alternative to freeways.
Custodial History
Angela Rooney donated the records in the 1990s. Mrs. Rooney along with her husband, Thomas Rooney, were key leaders in ECTC in the late 1960s.
Scope and Contents
The items include correspondence, clippings, government reports, legislative testimony, hearing transcripts, litigation, flyers, posters, maps, picket signs, press releases, and printed matter. Significant topics covered in the records include the fight to stop the construction of the Seven Sisters Bridge, I-66, I-95, the North Central Freeway, and the fight to save 69 government-confiscated homes in Northeast Washington, D.C.
Information about or from other local and national grassroots organizations involved in efforts to halt freeway construction appears in the records inlcuding: National Committee on the Transportation Crisis, Upper North East Coordinating Council, Brookland Civic Association, and Catholic Interracial Council. Clippings and articles cover D.C. and other urban areas working to block the construction of freeways, and other writings covering civil rights, urban renewal, and environmental issues.
Housing; Neighborhoods; Transportation; Community organization; Political activists; Urban renewal; Eminent domain; Brookland (Washington, D.C.); Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc); Correspondence; Legal documents
- Series 1: Alphabetical Files, 1960-1978
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains alphabetically arranged topical files that document ECTC's activities as well as those of other related organizations. The records were primarily maintained by Anne and Fred Huette -- Corresponding Secretary, and Vice Chair of ECTC, respectively; and Angela and Thomas Rooney -- Executive Secretary, and Associate Executive Secretary of ECTC, respectively. In order to maintain the original order, this series has been further arranged into subseries by the persons who maintained the records.
  - Subseries 1: Rooney Files, 1965-1975
    The files contain address lists, correspondence, publications, flyers, notes, and correspondence related to civic organizations in northeast Washington such as the Brookland Civic Association, Brookland Area Coordinating Council, and the Catholic Interracial Council. Reports from various governmental agencies, including the D.C. Office of Planning and Management, the National Capital Planning Commission, and the D.C. Department of Transportation appear in the files. Other file topics include parking in D.C., pollution, D.C. buses, home rule, housing, and zoning. Interfiled among the records are also a number of news clippings on the topics.
    - Address Lists thru Capitol East Gazette Newsnotes, 1966-1968, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Catholic Interracial Council - Addresses thru D.C. Government - Buses, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - D.C. Highway Department - Transportation Plan thru Freeways Correspondence, 11/25/1968, 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Freeway literature thru National TB and Respiratory Diseases Association, 1965, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Ralph Nader Playboy Interview thru Scientists Committee for Public Information, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Sister's College Property thru Zoning, July 14 1960, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Huette Files, 1968-1978
    This series includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, meeting minutes, clippings, and press releases related to the activities of ECTC and similar local organizations throughout the country. Of particular significance are records of the National Committee on the Transportation Crisis, the national organization that grew out of local freeway fights. Files cover the work of organizations in cities such as Boston, Philadelphia, Pittsburgh, Nashville, and Phoenix. Other topics and organizations found in the series include the Citizens Planning Coalition of D.C., the Brookland Area Coordinating Council, the Washington Planning Council, the Washington Lay Association, and the Upper Northeast Coordinating Council.
    - Air Quality thru Brookland - 12th Street, 1968-1975 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Air Quality thru Brookland - 12th Street, 1968-1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Air Quality thru Brookland - 12th Street, 1968-1975 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Brookland - 69 vacant homes thru Brookland metro station - parking, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Brookland Urban Design thru Conference, May 1981, June 1968 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Citizens for City Living Article 75 thru Environmental, 1973, 1969-1970 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Environmental education thru Freeway fight, 1978, 1968-1970 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Hamburger Verkehsverbund thru Metro - General, 1971, 1969-1971 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Metro - General thru National Committee on the Transportation Crisis - Boston Area, 1972, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - National Committee on the Transportation Crisis (NCTC) Clippings thru NCTC, 1969-1971, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - National Committee on the Transportation Crisis (NCTC) Clippings thru NCTC, 1969-1971, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - National Committee on the Transportation Crisis (NCTC) Clippings thru NCTC, 1969-1971, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - NCTC thru Newsletter, 1971-1972, August 1968 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - New York thru Pittsburgh, 1968-1975, October 1968 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Planning thru Statehood Party, 1969-1975, 1968-1972 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Planning thru Statehood Party, 1969-1975, 1968-1972 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Testimony thru Upper Northeast Coordinating Council (UNECC) - urban design study, 1967-1970, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - UNECC thru Washington D.C., 1973, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Washington D.C. thru Zoning, 1970, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1964-1980
  Much of the correspondence in this series is between members of ECTC and local politicians about highway legislation. Correspondents include public officials such as Walter Washington, Senator Joe Tydings, President Lyndon Johnson, Senator Paul Sarbanes, and Walter Tobriner, President of the Board of D.C. Commissioners (1964). The series also contains some reports, clippings, and legislative materials related to the correspondence. The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1964-1970 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1980 (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Series 3: Chronological, 1965-1974
  This series consists of a group of items that had no apparent arrangement nor fit in other series before processing. The materials were arranged chronologically to form this series. The series includes correspondence, reports, clippings, legislative testimony and bills, handwritten notes, newsletters, articles, and flyers.
  - Untitled, 1965-February 1969 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, March 1969-December 1971 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, January 1972-1974 (Box 25, Folder 1)
- Series 4: Legislative Materials, 1965-1975
  This series consists of testimony, statements, witness lists, and other background materials regarding hearings on highway construction before the D.C. City Council, D.C. Department of Highways and Traffic (DCDH), and U.S. Congressional Committees. Of particular significance are materials regarding hearings before the City Council on the Interstate Highway System (1967-1968), the DCDH (1965) on the North Central Freeway, and the House Committee on D.C. in the late 1960s on such issues as federal payment for highway funding and rapid rail transit. Copies of federal highway legislation in the Federal Register and Congressional Record are also included. Folders are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Congressional Record, 1968-1973 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Congressional Record, 1968-1973 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Congressional Record, 1968-1973 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Congressional Record, 1968-1973 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - D.C. Freeway hearings, 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - D.C. Freeway hearings, 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - D.C. Freeway hearings, 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Federal highway legislation, 1965-1970 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Federal highway legislation, 1965-1970 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Federal Register, October 23 1968 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Hearings, 1965-1971 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Hearings - House Committee on Public Works - "Major Highway Problems in D.C.", December 5-6 1967 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Hearing Report - House Subcommittee on Appropriations for Highways, 1970 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Hearings - Senate Committee on D.C., 1965-1969 (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Hearings - Senate Committee on D.C., 1965-1969 (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Hearings - Senate Committee on D.C., 1965-1969 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Hearings - Senate Committee on the Interior - Alternative Long-Range Energy Strategies, 1976 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - North-Central Freeway in D.C. and Montgomery and Prince Georges Counties Maryland, February 4 1965 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - North-Central Freeway in D.C. and Montgomery and Prince Georges Counties Maryland, February 4 1965 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - North-Central Freeway in D.C. and Montgomery and Prince Georges Counties Maryland, February 4 1965 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Testimony - Freeways, 1965-1967 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Testimony - Freeways, 1967-1973 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Testimony - Freeways, 1967-1973 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Testimony - Freeways, 1967-1973 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Testimony - Freeway, Undated (Box 30, Folder 4)
- Series 5: Printed Matter, 1967-1981
  Printed matter including pamphlets, journal articles, government publications, newsletters, and legislative materials on topics of interest to ECTC is contained in this series. Samples of journals represented include: Argus, Commonweal Papers, Engineering Opportunities, Environmental Science & Technology, and the New Republic. Publications of the National Capital Planning Commission, D.C. Government, Federal Water Pollution Control Administration, and the Maryland National Capital Park and Planning Commission are organizations prominently represented. Materials are arranged alphabetically first by journal title (if applicable), otherwise by author (if known), or title of article.
  - Americans for Democratic Action, Greater Washington Chapter," 20th Annual Roosevelt Day Dinner", 1970 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - "An Evening to Honor Julius Hobson", November 14, 1972 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Argus,"Freeway Pollution: Capital Punishment", May 1970 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Army Corps of Engineers, "Metropolitan Washington Area Water Supply Study for the Potomac Water Users", August 1979 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - "Atlanta Votes Yes on Rapid Transit", 1972 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Autofacts Publications, "People vs. Cars: The Rising Resentment of Against the Automobile", 1970 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Citizens' Advisory Committee on Environmental Quality, "Report to the President and to the Council on Environmental Quality", April 1972 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Citizens' Advisory Committee on Transportation Quality, "A Report to the Secretary of, Undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Commonweal Papers 1, "God", February 10, 1967 (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Commonweal Papers 2, "Jesus", 1967 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Urban Transportation, "Freeways and Our City", 1965 (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - Committee to Save Long Island Council Petition, 1971 (Box 31, Folder 12)
  - D.C. Government [publications], 1970-1981 (Box 31, Folder 13)
  - D.C. Government [publications], 1970-1981 (Box 31, Folder 14)
  - D.C. Government [publications], 1970-1981 (Box 31, Folder 15)
  - D.C. Government [publications], 1970-1981 (Box 31, Folder 16)
  - D.C. Government [publications], 1968-1981 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - D.C. Government [publications], 1968-1981 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - D.C. Government [publications], 1968-1981 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - D.C. Government [publications], 1968-1981 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - D.C. Government [publications], 1968-1981 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - D.C. Government [publications], 1968-1981 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Engineering Opportunities", 1969 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Environmental Action, "Freeways-Tearing Up Cities", October 1970 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Environmental Science and Technology, "Environmental Problems Have Little Respect for Political Boundaries", May 2, 1968 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Environmental Protection Agency, "Environmental Directory: Region III", 1970 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Envoy, "Students Design for Community", September 1981 (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Federal-Aid Highway Act of 1966 (P.L. 89-574), September 13, 1966 (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - Federal Water Pollution Control Administration, 1966-1969 (Box 32, Folder 13)
  - Federal Water Pollution Control Administration, 1966-1969 (Box 32, Folder 14)
  - Federal Water Pollution Control Administration, 1966-1969 (Box 32, Folder 15)
  - Greater Stockholm, 1972 (Box 32, Folder 16)
  - GW Times, "Images of Brookland" by Libby Hoffman, Undated (Box 32, Folder 17)
  - Hard Times, "Screeching Halt: U.S. Pulls Out of Pollution War" by James Ridgway, Undated (Box 32, Folder 18)
  - Hobson, Julius, "The Damned Information", 1971 (Box 32, Folder 19)
  - Kennan, Robert, "A Brief History of the Freeway Crisis", June 12, 1967 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Konstnarigutsmyckning i Stockholms, 1965 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Maryland National Capital Park and Planning Commission, Preliminary and Master Plans of Highways", 1967 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Maryland National Capital Park and Planning Commission, Preliminary and Master Plans of Highways", 1967 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Metromedia TV, "1985: A News Dramatization" (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments [publications], 1970-1974 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments [publications], 1970-1974 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Muskegon County Wastewater Management System, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - National Air Pollution Control Administration, "Community Support Bulletins", 1970 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - National Capital Planning Commission [publications], 1967-1968, 1975-1976 (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - National Capital Planning Commission [publications], 1967-1968, 1975-1976 (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - National Capital Planning Commission [publications], 1967-1968, 1975-1976 (Box 33, Folder 12)
  - National Capital Planning Commission [publications], 1967-1968, 1975-1976 (Box 33, Folder 13)
  - National Capital Planning Commission [publications], 1967-1968, 1975-1976 (Box 33, Folder 14)
  - National Capitol Redevelopment Agency, "Ft. Lincoln Urban Renewal Area", August 30, 1967 (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - Natural Resources Defense Council, Inc. Newsletters, Spring, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 16)
  - National Sciences Foundation, "Information, Perception and Regional Policy", 1975 (Box 33, Folder 17)
  - The New Republic, "Black Control of Cities", September 30, 1967 (Box 33, Folder 18)
  - The New Republic, Washington: The Lost City (Box 33, Folder 19)
  - The New Republic, "Washington: The Lost Colony", April 1966 (Box 33, Folder 20)
  - Penchey, Paul, et al, Catholic University, "Community Perceptions and Metropolitan Dynamics in an Urban Locality", 1971 (Box 33, Folder 21)
  - Pennsylvania Department of Transportation, "A New Highway is Born", Undated (Box 33, Folder 22)
  - Preliminary Operating Assumptions and Design Criteria for the Downtown Design and Development Study", September, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 23)
  - "Public Transportation in Highway Decisions", May 25, 1972 (Box 33, Folder 24)
  - Railroad Electrification, Vol. 3, 1970 (Box 33, Folder 25)